<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd">
<?rfc compact="yes"?>
<?rfc subcompact="no"?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc strict="yes"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc tocdepth="4"?>

<rfc category="std" ipr="trust200902" docName="draft-ietf-precis-7700bis-00" obsoletes="7700">

  <front>

    <title abbrev="PRECIS: Nickname">Preparation, Enforcement, and Comparison of Internationalized Strings Representing Nicknames</title>

    <author initials="P." surname="Saint-Andre" fullname="Peter Saint-Andre">
      <organization>Filament</organization>
      <address>
        <email>peter@filament.com</email>
        <uri>https://filament.com/</uri>
      </address>
    </author>

    <date/>

    <area>Applications</area>
    <workgroup>PRECIS</workgroup>

    <keyword>nickname</keyword>
    <keyword>SIP</keyword>
    <keyword>SIMPLE</keyword>
    <keyword>XMPP</keyword>
    <keyword>MSRP</keyword>
    <keyword>XCON</keyword>
    <keyword>chatrooms</keyword>

    <abstract>
      <t>This document describes methods for handling Unicode strings representing memorable, human-friendly names (called "nicknames", "display names", or "petnames") for people, devices, accounts, websites, and other entities.  This document obsoletes RFC 7700.</t>
    </abstract>

  </front>


  <middle>

  <section title="Introduction" anchor="intro">

    <section title="Overview" anchor="overview">
      <t>A number of technologies and applications provide the ability for a person to choose a memorable, human-friendly name in a communications context, or to set such a name for another entity such as a device, account, contact, or website.  Such names are variously called "nicknames" (e.g., in chat room applications), "display names" (e.g., in Internet mail), or "petnames" (see <xref target='PETNAME-SYSTEMS'/>); for consistency, these are all called "nicknames" in this document.</t>
      <t>Nicknames are commonly supported in technologies for textual chat rooms, e.g., Internet Relay Chat <xref target='RFC2811'/> and multi-party chat technologies based on the Extensible Messaging and Presence Protocol (XMPP) <xref target='RFC6120'/> <xref target='XEP-0045'/>, the Message Session Relay Protocol (MSRP) <xref target='RFC4975'/> <xref target='RFC7701'/>, and Centralized Conferencing (XCON) <xref target='RFC5239'/> <xref target='XCON-SYSTEM'/>.  Recent chat room technologies also allow internationalized nicknames because they support characters from outside the ASCII range <xref target='RFC20'/>, typically by means of the Unicode character set <xref target='Unicode'/>.  Although such nicknames tend to be used primarily for display purposes, they are sometimes used for programmatic purposes as well (e.g., kicking users or avoiding nickname conflicts).</t>
      <t>A similar usage enables a person to set their own preferred display name or to set a preferred display name for another user (e.g., the "display-name" construct in the Internet message format <xref target='RFC5322'/> and <xref target='XEP-0172'/> in XMPP).</t>
      <t>Memorable, human-friendly names are also used in contexts other than personal messaging, such as names for devices (e.g., in a network visualization application), websites (e.g., for bookmarks in a web browser), accounts (e.g., in a web interface for a list of payees in a bank account), people (e.g., in a contact list application), and the like.</t>
      <t>The rules specified in this document can be applied in all of the foregoing contexts.</t>
      <t>To increase the likelihood that memorable, human-friendly names will work in ways that make sense for typical users throughout the world, this document defines rules for preparing, enforcing, and comparing internationalized nicknames.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Terminology" anchor="terms">
      <t>Many important terms used in this document are defined in <xref target='RFC7564'/>, <xref target='RFC6365'/>, and <xref target='Unicode'/>.</t>
      <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT", "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "NOT RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this document are to be interpreted as described in <xref target='RFC2119'/>.</t>
    </section>

  </section>

  <section title='Nickname Profile' anchor='rules'>

    <section title='Rules' anchor='rules-rules'>
      <t>The following rules apply within the Nickname profile of the PRECIS FreeformClass.</t>
      <t>
        <list style='numbers'>
          <t>Width Mapping Rule: There is no width-mapping rule (such a rule is not necessary because width mapping is performed as part of normalization using Normalization Form KC (NFKC) as specified below).</t>
          <t>Additional Mapping Rule: The additional mapping rule consists of the following sub-rules.
            <list>
              <t>Any instances of non-ASCII space MUST be mapped to ASCII space (U+0020); a non-ASCII space is any Unicode code point having a general category of "Zs", naturally with the exception of U+0020.</t>
              <t>Any instances of the ASCII space character at the beginning or end of a nickname MUST be removed (e.g., "stpeter&#160;" is mapped to "stpeter").</t>
              <t>Interior sequences of more than one ASCII space character MUST be mapped to a single ASCII space character (e.g., "St&#160;&#160;Peter" is mapped to "St&#160;Peter").</t>
            </list>
          </t>

          <t>Case Mapping Rule: Unicode Default Case Folding MUST be applied,
      as defined in the Unicode Standard
          <xref target='Unicode'/> (at the time of this writing, the
          algorithm is specified in Chapter 3 of <xref
          target='Unicode7.0'/>).  In applications
      that prohibit conflicting nicknames, this rule helps to reduce
      the possibility of confusion by ensuring that nicknames
      differing only by case (e.g., "stpeter" vs. "StPeter") would not
      be presented to a human user at the same time.</t>

          <t>Normalization Rule: The string MUST be normalized using Unicode NFKC.  Because NFKC is more "aggressive" in finding matches than other normalization forms (in the terminology of Unicode, it performs both canonical and compatibility decomposition before recomposing code points), this rule helps to reduce the possibility of confusion by increasing the number of characters that would match (e.g., U+2163 ROMAN NUMERAL FOUR would match the combination of U+0049 LATIN CAPITAL LETTER I and U+0056 LATIN CAPITAL LETTER V).</t>
          <t>Directionality Rule: There is no directionality rule. The "Bidi Rule" (defined in <xref target='RFC5893'/>) and similar rules are unnecessary and inapplicable to nicknames, because it is perfectly acceptable for a given nickname to be presented differently in different layout systems (e.g., a user interface that is configured to handle primarily a right-to-left script versus an interface that is configured to handle primarily a left-to-right script), as long as the presentation is consistent in any given layout system.</t>
        </list>
      </t>
    </section>

    <section title='Preparation' anchor='rules-prep'>
      <t>An entity that prepares a string for subsequent enforcement according to this profile MUST ensure that the string consists only of Unicode code points that conform to the FreeformClass string class defined in <xref target='RFC7564'/>.  In addition, the entity MUST ensure that the string is encoded as UTF-8 <xref target='RFC3629'/>.</t>
    </section>


    <section title='Enforcement' anchor='rules-enforce'>
<t>An entity that performs enforcement according to this profile MUST
  prepare a string as described in <xref target='rules-prep'/> and MUST also apply the
  following rules specified in <xref target='rules-rules'/> in the order shown:
<list style="numbers">
<?rfc subcompact="yes"?>
<t>Additional Mapping Rule</t>
<t>Normalization Rule</t>
<t>Directionality Rule</t>
</list></t>
<?rfc subcompact="no"?>

<t>After all of the foregoing rules have been enforced, the entity MUST
  ensure that the nickname is not zero bytes in length (this is done
  after enforcing the rules to prevent applications from mistakenly
  omitting a nickname entirely, because when internationalized
  characters are accepted, a non-empty sequence of characters can
  result in a zero-length nickname after canonicalization).</t>
</section>

    <section title="Comparison" anchor="rules-comp">
<t>  An entity that performs comparison of two strings according to this
  profile MUST prepare each string as specified in <xref target='rules-prep'/> and
  MUST apply the following rules specified in <xref target='rules-rules'/> in the order
  shown:
<?rfc subcompact="yes"?>
<list style="numbers">
<t>Additional Mapping Rule</t>
<t>Case Mapping Rule</t>
<t>Normalization Rule</t>
<t>Directionality Rule</t>
</list></t>
<?rfc subcompact="no"?>
<t>  The two strings are to be considered equivalent if they are an exact
  octet-for-octet match (sometimes called "bit-string identity").
</t>
    </section>

  </section>

  <section title="Examples" anchor="examples">
    <t>The following examples illustrate a small number of nicknames that are consistent with the format defined above, along with the output string resulting from application of the PRECIS rules (note that the characters &lt; and &gt; are used to delineate the actual nickname and are not part of the nickname strings).</t>
    <figure>
      <preamble>Table 1: A Sample of Legal Nicknames</preamble>
      <artwork><![CDATA[
+---------------------------+-----------------------------------+
| # | Nickname              | Output for Comparison             |
+---------------------------+-----------------------------------+
| 1 | <Foo>                 | <foo>                             |
+---------------------------+-----------------------------------+
| 2 | <foo>                 | <foo>                             |
+---------------------------+-----------------------------------+
| 3 | <Foo Bar>             | <foo bar>                         |
+---------------------------+-----------------------------------+
| 4 | <foo bar>             | <foo bar>                         |
+---------------------------+-----------------------------------+
| 5 | <&#x3A3;>             | GREEK SMALL LETTER SIGMA (U+03C3) |
+---------------------------+-----------------------------------+
| 6 | <&#x3C3;>             | GREEK SMALL LETTER SIGMA (U+03C3) |
+---------------------------+-----------------------------------+
| 7 | <&#x3C2;>             | GREEK SMALL LETTER SIGMA (U+03C3) |
+---------------------------+-----------------------------------+
| 8 | <&#x265A;>            | BLACK CHESS KING (U+265A)         |
+---------------------------+-----------------------------------+
| 9 | <Richard &#x2163;>    | <richard iv>                      |
+---------------------------+-----------------------------------+
      ]]></artwork>
    </figure>

    <t>Regarding examples 5, 6, and 7: applying Unicode Default Case Folding
  to GREEK CAPITAL LETTER SIGMA (U+03A3) results in GREEK SMALL LETTER
  SIGMA (U+03C3), and the same is true of GREEK SMALL LETTER FINAL
  SIGMA (U+03C2); therefore, the comparison operation defined in
  <xref target="rules-comp"/> would result in matching of the nicknames in examples 5,
  6, and 7.


    Regarding example 8: symbol characters such as BLACK CHESS KING
    (U+265A) are allowed by the PRECIS FreeformClass and thus can be
    used in nicknames.  Regarding example 9: applying Unicode Default
    Case Folding to ROMAN NUMERAL FOUR (U+2163) results in SMALL ROMAN
    NUMERAL FOUR (U+2173), and applying NFKC to SMALL ROMAN NUMERAL
    FOUR (U+2173) results in LATIN SMALL LETTER I (U+0069) LATIN SMALL
    LETTER V (U+0086).</t>
  </section>

  <section title="Use in Application Protocols" anchor="use">
    <t>This specification defines only the PRECIS-based rules for handling of nickname strings.  It is the responsibility of an application protocol (e.g., MSRP, XCON, or XMPP) or application definition to specify the protocol slots in which nickname strings can appear, the entities that are expected to enforce the rules governing nickname strings, and when in protocol processing or interface handling the rules need to be enforced.  See Section 6 of <xref target='RFC7564'/> for guidelines about using PRECIS profiles in applications.</t>
    <t>Above and beyond the PRECIS-based rules specified here, application protocols can also define application-specific rules governing nickname strings (rules regarding the minimum or maximum length of nicknames, further restrictions on allowable characters or character ranges, safeguards to mitigate the effects of visually similar characters, etc.).</t>
    <t>Naturally, application protocols can also specify rules governing the actual use of nicknames in applications (reserved nicknames, authorization requirements for using nicknames, whether certain nicknames can be prohibited, handling of duplicates, the relationship between nicknames and underlying identifiers such as SIP URIs or Jabber IDs, etc.).</t>
    <t>Entities that enforce the rules specified in this document are encouraged to be liberal in what they accept by following this procedure:</t>
    <t>
      <list style='numbers'>
        <t>Where possible, map characters (e.g, through width mapping, additional mapping, case mapping, or normalization) and accept the mapped string.</t>
        <t>If mapping is not possible (e.g., because a character is disallowed in the FreeformClass), reject the string.</t>
      </list>
    </t>
  </section>

  <section title="IANA Considerations" anchor="iana">
    <t>The IANA shall add the following entry to the PRECIS Profiles Registry:</t>
    <t>
      <list style='hanging'>
        <t hangText='Name:'>Nickname</t>
        <t hangText='Base Class:'>FreeformClass</t>
        <t hangText='Applicability:'>Nicknames in messaging and text conferencing technologies; petnames for devices, accounts, and people; and other uses of nicknames or petnames.</t>
        <t hangText='Replaces:'>None</t>
        <t hangText='Width Mapping Rule:'>None (handled via NFKC)</t>
        <t hangText='Additional Mapping Rule:'>Map non-ASCII space characters to ASCII space, strip leading and trailing space characters, map interior sequences of multiple space characters to a single ASCII space.</t>
        <t hangText='Case Mapping Rule:'>Map uppercase and titlecase characters to lowercase using Unicode Default Case Folding.</t>
        <t hangText='Normalization Rule:'>NFKC</t>
        <t hangText='Directionality Rule:'>None</t>
        <t hangText='Enforcement:'>To be specified by applications.</t>
        <t hangText='Specification:'>RFC 7700 (this document)</t>
      </list>
    </t>
  </section>

  <section title="Security Considerations" anchor="security">
    <section title="Reuse of PRECIS" anchor="security-precis">
      <t>The security considerations described in <xref target="RFC7564"/> apply to the FreeformClass string class used in this document for nicknames.</t>
    </section>
    <section title="Reuse of Unicode" anchor="security-unicode">
      <t>The security considerations described in <xref target='UTS39'/> apply to the use of Unicode characters in nicknames.</t>
    </section>
    <section title="Visually Similar Characters" anchor="security-similar">
      <t><xref target='RFC7564'/> describes some of the security considerations related to visually similar characters, also called "confusable characters" or "confusables".</t>
      <t>Although the mapping rules defined in <xref target='rules'/> of this document are designed, in part, to reduce the possibility of confusion about nicknames, this document does not provide more-detailed recommendations regarding the handling of visually similar characters, such as those provided in <xref target='UTS39'/>.</t>
    </section>
  </section>

  </middle>

  <back>

    <references title="Normative References">


<?rfc include="reference.RFC.2119.xml"?>
<?rfc include="reference.RFC.3629.xml"?>
<?rfc include="reference.RFC.5893.xml"?>
<?rfc include="reference.RFC.6365.xml"?>
<?rfc include="reference.RFC.7564.xml"?>

<reference anchor="Unicode" target="http://www.unicode.org/versions/latest/">
  <front>
    <title>The Unicode Standard</title>
    <author>
      <organization>The Unicode Consortium</organization>
    </author>
    <date />
  </front>
</reference>

<reference anchor="Unicode7.0" target="http://www.unicode.org/versions/Unicode7.0.0/">
  <front>
    <title>The Unicode Standard, Version 7.0.0</title>
    <author>
      <organization>The Unicode Consortium</organization>
    </author>
    <date year="2014" />
  </front>
</reference>

<reference anchor="UTS39" target='http://unicode.org/reports/tr39/'>
  <front>
    <title>Unicode Technical Standard #39: Unicode Security Mechanisms</title>
    <author>
      <organization>The Unicode Consortium</organization>
    </author>
    <date month="November" year="2013" />
  </front>
</reference>

    </references>

    <references title="Informative References">



<reference  anchor='RFC20' target='http://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc20'>
<front>
<title>ASCII format for network interchange</title>
<author initials='V.G.' surname='Cerf' fullname='V.G. Cerf'><organization /></author>
<date year='1969' month='October' />
</front>
<seriesInfo name='STD' value='80'/>
<seriesInfo name='RFC' value='20'/>
<seriesInfo name='DOI' value='10.17487/RFC0020'/>
</reference>

<?rfc include="reference.RFC.2811.xml"?>
<?rfc include="reference.RFC.4975.xml"?>
<?rfc include="reference.RFC.5239.xml"?>
<?rfc include="reference.RFC.5322.xml"?>
<?rfc include="reference.RFC.6120.xml"?>


<!--I-D.boulton-xcon-session-chat: Expired -->
<reference anchor='XCON-SYSTEM'>
<front>
<title>Chatrooms within a Centralized Conferencing (XCON) System</title>
<author initials='M' surname='Barnes' fullname='Mary Barnes'>
    <organization />
</author>
<author initials='C' surname='Boulton' fullname='Chris Boulton'>
    <organization />
</author>
<author initials='S' surname='Loreto' fullname='Salvatore Loreto'>
    <organization />
</author>
<date month='July' day='16' year='2012' />
<abstract><t>The document "A Framework for Centralized Conferencing" defines a centralized conference as both signaling and protocol agnostic.  The primary examples within this framework focus on audio and video as the media types for the session.  This document provides an overview of the mechanisms defined in the centralized conferencing framework that can be used to support multi-user chat.  In addition, the document describes additional functionality and requirements necessary to provide feature rich functionality.</t></abstract>
</front>
<seriesInfo name='Work in Progress,' value='draft-boulton-xcon-session-chat-08' />

</reference>

<!--I-D.ietf-simple-chat:  Companion document, RFC 7701 -->

<reference anchor='RFC7701' target="http://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc7701">
<front>
<title>Multi-party Chat Using the Message Session Relay Protocol (MSRP)</title>
<author initials='A' surname='Niemi' fullname='Aki Niemi'>
    <organization />
</author>
<author initials='M' surname='Garcia-Martin' fullname='Miguel Garcia-Martin'>
    <organization />
</author>
<author initials='G' surname='Sandbakken' fullname='Geir Sandbakken'>
    <organization />
</author>
<date month='December' year='2015' />
<abstract><t>The Message Session Relay Protocol (MSRP) defines a mechanism for sending instant messages within a peer-to-peer session, negotiated using the Session Initiation Protocol (SIP) and the Session Description Protocol (SDP).  This document defines the necessary tools for establishing multi-party chat sessions, or chat rooms, using MSRP.</t></abstract>
</front>
<seriesInfo name='RFC' value='7701'/>
<seriesInfo name="DOI" value="10.17487/RFC7701"/>
</reference>



<reference anchor="XEP-0045" target="http://xmpp.org/extensions/xep-0045.html">
  <front>
    <title>Multi-User Chat</title>
    <author initials="P." surname="Saint-Andre" fullname="Peter Saint-Andre">
      <organization/>
      <address>
        <email>stpeter@jabber.org</email>
      </address>
    </author>
    <date day="08" month="February" year="2012"/>
  </front>
  <seriesInfo name="XSF XEP" value="0045"/>
  <format type="HTML" target="http://xmpp.org/extensions/xep-0045.html"/>
</reference>

<reference anchor="XEP-0172" target="http://xmpp.org/extensions/xep-0172.html">
  <front>
    <title>User Nickname</title>
    <author initials="P." surname="Saint-Andre" fullname="Peter Saint-Andre">
      <organization/>
      <address>
        <email>stpeter@jabber.org</email>
      </address>
    </author>
    <author initials="V." surname="Mercier" fullname="Valerie Mercier">
      <organization/>
      <address>
        <email>valerie.mercier@orange-ftgroup.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>
    <date day="21" month="March" year="2012"/>
  </front>
  <seriesInfo name="XSF XEP" value="0172"/>
</reference>


<reference anchor="PETNAME-SYSTEMS" target="http://www.skyhunter.com/marcs/petnames/IntroPetNames.html">
  <front>
    <title>An Introduction to Petname Systems</title>
    <author initials="M." surname="Stiegler" fullname="Marc Stiegler">
      <organization/>
      <address>
        <email></email>
      </address>
    </author>
    <date month="February" year="2005"/>
  </front>
  <seriesInfo name="updated June" value="2012"/>
</reference>

    </references>

  <section title="Acknowledgements" anchor="acks">
    <t>Thanks to Kim Alvefur, Mary Barnes, Ben Campbell, Dave Cridland, Miguel Garcia, Salvatore Loreto, Enrico Marocco, Matt Miller, and Yoshiro YONEYA for their reviews and comments.</t>
    <t>Paul Kyzivat and Melinda Shore reviewed the document for the General Area Review Team and Operations Directorate, respectively.</t>
    <t>During IESG review, Ben Campbell and Kathleen Moriarty provided comments that led to further improvements.</t>
    <t>Thanks to Matt Miller as Document Shepherd, Pete Resnick and Andrew Sullivan as IANA Designated Experts, Marc Blanchet and Alexey Melnikov as working group Chairs, and Barry Leiba as Area Director.</t>
    <t>The author wishes to acknowledge Cisco Systems, Inc., for employing him during his work on earlier draft versions of this document.</t>
  </section>

  </back>

</rfc>
